# **Abdul Khalil**

# **UK Citizen/Canadian PR**

# https://www.linkedin.com/in/abdulkhalil/ rehmank11@gmail.com

## Position Title: Product Manager/Product Owner/Business Analyst

#### **Summary:**

A successful project manager and a business analyst with **five years** of experience in agile software development, where a Kanban approach combined with scrum was used to deliver several software and digital products by decomposing epics into user stories. Offering excellent skills, knowledge and experience in project and product management, testing and business analysis which is complemented by a verified track record of working within cross functional teams to drive projects to completion.

### **Education:**

University of Toronto, Toronto, Canada

| University of Toronto, Toronto, Canada                                       |             |
|--|-------------|
| <ul> <li>Coding boot camp, Full Stack Developer (Sep 31 2021)</li> </ul>     | 2021        |
| International Institute of Business Analysts, IIBA                           |             |
| <ul> <li>Certified Business Analyst Professional, CBAP, Candidate</li> </ul> | 2021        |
| Project Management Institute, PMI  |             |
| <ul> <li>Project Management Professional, PMP®, #2927346</li> </ul>          | 2020        |
| University of Nottingham, Nottingham, United Kingdom                         |             |
| <ul> <li>M.Sc. Honours Degree, Chemistry, First</li> </ul>                   | 2015 - 2016 |
| B.Sc. Honours Degree, Chemistry, <b>First</b>                                | 2012 -2015  |
|  |             |

**Projects:** Client Journey and Onboarding, Audit Maps/Trails, Data Acquisition, User Settings/Configurations, Client Portal, CRM, Contacts, Billing/Payments, Reporting, Dashboards, Document Generation and E-Sign

**Technical Skills: JIRA, Confluence** and Bitbucket, **MS Visio, Figma, Balsamiq**, TeamCity, GIT, Source Tree, Tortoise SVN, MS Suite, Basic HTML, **SQL**, and Shell Scripting. Soft skills; Interviews, workshops, focus groups, external customer evaluations (ECE), demonstrations, workflow analysis and brain storming

### **Skills:**

- Bachelor of Science and Master of Science in Chemistry, First class from University of Nottingham
- Project Management Professional, PMP certified (similar to PRINCE2), and have excellent understanding of project management methodologies, project documentation (33 documents and 18 baselines and subplans), and project lifecycle documented in the PMBOK guide 6th edition
- Gaining excellent current working knowledge of BA practices from **BABOK guide V3** and enrolled in becoming a **full stack developer** and will be adept in technologies such as **MERN stack** development
- Five years of experience gained by working at Newton Connectivity Systems, SCIEX, Laurentian/B2B Bank Canada, and Santander bank, by successfully eliciting and implementing requirements for banking, e-commerce, SAAS/SAP, pharmaceutical, insurance products
- Excellent experience in an agile process implementation demonstrated by successfully introducing story point estimation via t-shirt sizing method and Fibonacci sequence to estimate sprints and epics.
- Working directly with the CEO and VP's to deliver new features from concept to delivery, scoping of
  products and milestones to ensure commitments were achieved within timeframe by grooming product
  backlog, prioritizing and identifying technical debt
- Managed **medium-large** sized (10-20 people) projects by honing the role of **scrum master on a daily basis**, completing over **1000 scrums** and outlining **minimum viable product (MVP)** for deliverables by documenting over 40 **UML** diagrams, **business cases** and planning over 100 sprints
- Rigorously managed scope to ensure commitments were achieved within timeframe cost, and quality
  by reviewing requirements, timeboxing and prioritizing 1000 + JIRA tickets, allocating story points
  and identifying verification and technical debt to deliver software through continuous integration

# **Experience:**

## **Product/ProjectManager**

Newton Connectivity Systems, Toronto, Canada

Jul 2020 – Current

- Owning and regularly grooming the backlog for the Velocity software (SAAS/SAP) and Managing projects involving third party integrations such as Manulife, OPTA, Twilio, OneSpan, and WalkMe to aid the broker/lender mortgage approval process
- Acting product manager for the app dev cross functional team. Identifying and prioritizing opportunities to consistently realize product strategy and planning for release. Leading a team of nine people including four developers, four testers and a UI/UX architect
- Responsible for managing entire QA team with a fellow BA by allocating resources to upcoming projects and sprints. Managing all customer field issues from customer care by prioritizing and assigning them to relevant members for investigation
- Provided **leadership** and **motivation** to project team to obtain a high level of co-operation especially during the closing phases of the project by **valuing** and appreciating team effort, managing workload and praising hard work of others by **leveraging** interpersonal and teamwork skills

# **Business Analyst**

LBC/B2B Bank, Toronto, Canada

Feb 2020 – Jun 2020

**Project:** Upgrading Laurentian/B2B Bank online digital platform and validating online secure site

- Reduced product backlog by 35% and re-prioritized future work by organising backlog cleaning up sessions with product managers and relevant stake holders to review all remaining items
- Documented business and functional rules of online LBC/B2B digital platform in Confluence by working closely with product manager to upgrade online website to improve user experience. Worked in an agile scrum fashion to facilitate web development and mobile testing
- Created and documented workflows for opening new GICs, chequing/savings accounts and online mortgage payments functionality and tested systems in different environments to verify requirements
- Tested various transactions such as deposits, transfers, linking accounts, GIC investments, payment of bills, profile settings, and payee/vendor testing to ensure accurate movement of money. Documented Equifax AML logic for verifying new accounts and CERB implementations for COVID-19

### **Business Analyst**

SCIEX, Toronto, Canada (Danaher, Fortune 500)

Jan 2017 - Oct 2019

- Demonstrated outstanding final **product delivery** by receiving least customer field issues
- Gathered **requirements** by conducting and leading over 200 meetings with **stakeholders** and carrying out over 50 interviews such as **external customer evaluations** and voice of customer to gather project requirements and deliver 20 use case models in **MS Visio** and Confluence
- Instigated correct **agile** practices by completing over 100 sprints with a **product owner**, 15 developers, 20 **testers** and two **UI/UX** consultants in two-week sprint cadences, which included code reviews, **scrums**/daily stand-ups, and mini-meetings to ultimately resolve over 300 **defects/bugs**
- Demonstrated excellent knowledge on **SDLC** and development tools by setting up and maintaining over 50 **automated tests** to run in DevOps environment by using tools such as GIT, SourceTree, and VMware to run tests on various levels on the integration build on a regular basis for **QA**
- Documented four use cases and over 20 alternate main cases by conducting research/document analysis from legacy implementations and running requirements workshops to deliver documentation for QA purposes such as BRD, UND, SRS, SSR, FS, release notes, backlog, and defect prioritization lists